<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonicion against astrology iudiciall and other curiosities, that raigne novv in the vvorld: written in the french tonge by Ihon Caluine and translated into English, by G.G.</title>
            <title>Advertissement contre l'astrologie judiciaire. English</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843176</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 453:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonicion against astrology iudiciall and other curiosities, that raigne novv in the vvorld: written in the french tonge by Ihon Caluine and translated into English, by G.G.</title>
                  <title>Advertissement contre l'astrologie judiciaire. English</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Gilby, Goddred.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Roulande Hall, dwellyng in Golding lane, at the signe of the thre arrowes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.G. = Goddred Gilby.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Advertissement contre l'astrologie judiciaire.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Against astrology iudiciall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7889:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7889:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN AD<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monicion againſt ASTROLOGY IVDICIALL and other curioſities, that raigne now in the world: written in the french tonge by IHON CALVINE and tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe, by G. G.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Auſten of the citie of god. Lib. 5. cap. 7.</bibl>
               <p>It is not without cauſe that men ſuppoſe that when the Aſtrologours do meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly in their anſweres declare manye truthes, the ſame is done by a ſecrete in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of wicked ſpirites, whoſe care is to faſten and confirme in mens mindes theſe falſe and hurtfull opinions of ſtat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie deſtinies, and not by any art or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the noting and beholding of the byrth ſtar. For there is no ſuch art at all.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande Hall, dwellyng in Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding lane, at the ſigne of the thre arrowes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7889:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe the iudicials of Aſtrology <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> caſting of figurs to tel fortunes ſeme rather childiſhe plaies then weighty matters for graue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be occupied with al. In ſo much as god himſelf threatneth that he will ſend out his plages &amp; powre forth his iudgements vpon the wicked, &amp; their ſo thſaiers and ſtargaſers ſhall not know how nor when ſuch things ſhal com vpon them. And our experience teacheth vs the ſame in the late famine among vs, in the loſing of Calis, in the burning of Pouls and the deſtruction of other cities and contreis. Therfore am I bold thogh I be but a child to offer to the world ſoch things concerning the curioſitie of that art, and the abuſe of the ſame, as I bothe learned at the mouth of maiſter Caluine and red in his bokes: &amp; the rather becauſe I do ſe that my former labor in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation of that epiſtle of <hi>Cicero</hi> vnto his brother <hi>Quintus</hi> hath not bene reiected.</p>
            <p>Now again if my labors may be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any, I ſhal praiſe god, &amp; giue my ſelf to further ſtudies that I mai more ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mire gods glory, &amp; according to my ſmal talent profit his church, which thing that lord that is the only author of al wiſdom and geuer of all goodnes grant me to do always to my lyues end. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:7889:2"/>
            <head>An admonicion AGAYNST ASTROLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye Iudiciall, and other curioſities.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AINCT PAVL</hi> DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth admoniſhe vs of one thing very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the which not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wythſtandynge fewe take good heede: to witte, that they which care nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for the walking in a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience doe turne away and wander from the faith, for he dothe meane that they which doe pollute their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in geuyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ouer to wickednes are not worthy to be mainteined in the pure knowledge of God: but rather deſerue to be made blinde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entent that they may be deceiued by diuerſe errours and lies. And it is a wonderful mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that we ſet ſo litle by it: ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery day we ſe ſo great experience therof euen before our eies.</p>
            <p>Thys is certayne that God dothe
<pb facs="tcp:7889:3"/> neuer take away hys truthe from them vnto whome he hath geuen ſome taſte thereof, onles it be for this cauſe that they haue not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely receaued it, but haue rather abuſed it to a foliſhe ambition or to others carnall affections. In very dede ſeing that thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſome portion of ſyluer are ſo carefull to keape it ſafely, it is alſo good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that this ineſtimable treaſure of the Goſpell (ſeing God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed this riches vpon vs) be as it were ſurely cloſed vp in a good con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is the right coffre (if I may ſo terme it) to kepe it ſafe and ſure that it ſhould not be ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from vs by the malice of ſatan.</p>
            <p>And what cometh to paſſe in the ſeede hereof. The moſte parte cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſethe the word of God to ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only to this purpoſe that they may haue ſomethyng to talke vpon in company. And one ſort are led with ambition hereunto, another ſorte ſeke their own gayn, yea and there be ſome that abuſe it to practyſe
<pb facs="tcp:7889:3"/> baudri therby to get acceſſe to ther wemen &amp; ladies. Very many know not to what purpoſe they ſhold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to vnderſtand it: ſaue only that they are aſhamed to ſe others take holde vpon it, and that they ſhould be ueſpiſed by their ignorance. In ſo much almoſt all a few excepted, doe turne this doctrine of ſaluacion into a certaine prophane philoſphy I know not how. The which this is ſuche a vilany that God can not ſuffer it: becauſe that this his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word is a thing more holy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it ſhoulde be thus abuſed. It oght to bellyuely &amp; of ſuche force &amp; efficacy that it ſhuld perce thorow, the herts, for to examine and try all that is within the man euen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the mary of the bones as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be aſhamed thereof and cauſe it to ſerue for a paſtyme: thinke we that God can ſuffer ſuche a contempt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power thereof. It oght to reproue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as S. Paul ſaith) to thintent that he may lerne to condempne himſelf &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7889:4"/> to giue the glory vnto God in hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bling himſelf. If any then turne it to boaſtyng and to vaine glory: is not this an abuſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſerueth gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. It ought to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme &amp; change vs into the image of God and to reforme that which is ours in vs. If any take occaſion vnder the cloke therof to mantain themſelues in theſe vices, muſt it not come to paſſe, that God wyll puniſhe not onely ſuche an abuſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> turne the men into poyſon but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſuch a ſacrilege as cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of good lyfe to ſerue as a licence to all euell. It nedeth not here now to ciphre out euery perticular of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of the moſt part of them that ſay that they doo know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe of the Goſpel. For ſo muche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may ſee in effecte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> certaine where as they ſhould be amended are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come rather worſſe. The reſidue kepe ſtyll their olde courſe, at the leaſt a man can perceiue but ſmall Amendement. Sainct Paul ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the change that ſhould be in
<pb facs="tcp:7889:4"/> the Chriſtians and of the fruyts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould procede forth of their newe life when they are reformed to the image of the ſon of God ſaith, that he that hath robbed ſhuld robbe no more. Whereby he meaneth that if we haue folowed any euell trade ſo ſoone as God hath geuen vs the grace to know his wyll we muſte turne backward. But in the ſtead hereof thoſe that at this day count themſelues Chriſtians, diſpenſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> themſelues without ſcruple of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, to be at the leaſte like vnto others, ſo that he which was acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to be an adulter dothe yet ſtill continew in his vilany. The playes and paſtymes yea the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies ar as outragious emongs them as they were afore time. The ſuperfluitees and pompes are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed as thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs indifferent althogh a man may ſee that they ſerue for nothing but for prid ambition and all vanitie. Moreouer euery eſtate wyll haue his Goſpel a parte, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding as the forge it for their appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tite,
<pb facs="tcp:7889:5"/> ſo that there is as great diuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie betwixt the goſpel of the court and that of lawyers &amp; Iuſticiaries and that of the marchants and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune multitude as is betwyxt the mony made of manye diuers coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes: Saue that they all haue one marke a like (that is) that they are of the worlde. Whereby they haue no agrement w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus, who wolde ſeperate vs from the world.</p>
            <p>Therfore it is good reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they that thus diſhonour the doctrine of the Goſpel ſhoulde be confounded, and that God ſhould ſet them forth as a mocking ſtocke vnto eueri ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeing that they haue bene the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that his holy name hath bene blaſpemed. It is moſte right alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde make them foliſhe and depryue them of all reaſon &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, ſeing that they colde take no profite of that wyſdome which is had in admiration of the Angels of paradiſe. Beholde this day whence ſo many foliſhe opinions do aryſe, or rather dooting madnes which
<pb facs="tcp:7889:5"/> haue nether colour nor appearance and yet are they receaued as they were reuelations come down from heauen finally ſeing that preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the very roote of all hereſies wandring phantaſies &amp; of all falſe and wicked opinions: it is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile thoghe God do let them falle into ſo mani folies which haue not kept the right rule how they ſhuld abide in the obedience of his truth: which is to humble themſelf in his feare. And for ſo muche as this vice is as common now a dayes as euer it was: we ſee alſo what frutes it hath: ſo that all the errours which are abrode in all the worlde are no other thyng but ſo many puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments becauſe that men haue abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the holy worde of God. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I doe not intend to make a longe rehearſe of them all: forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the nomber would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. I will holde my ſelf conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with one example alone.</p>
            <p>There hath bene of long time a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe curioſitie to iudge by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars
<pb facs="tcp:7889:6"/> of all things what ſhould chaunce vnto men: and thence to enquire &amp; take councel as touching thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters which are to be done. But we wil by and by God willing declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is nothing but a diueliſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtition. Yea and it hath bene reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a common conſent as perui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious to man kind. And yet at this day it hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vpperhand in ſuch ſorte that many whych thynk themſelues wytty men yea &amp; haue bene ſo iudged: are as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched therwith. But althoughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God had not reueled in our tyme the ſincere truth of his Goſpel (not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtandyng ſeyng he hath raiſed vp the humaine ſciences which are apte and profitable to the guyding of oure life and in ſeruing to oure profite may alſo ſerue to his glory) yet had he iuſt occaſyon (I ſay) to puniſhe theyr ingratytude whych not contenting themſelues with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things which are ſubſtancyall and grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do through an outragious pride deſier to flye
<pb facs="tcp:7889:6"/> to and fro in the air. But now ſince he hath giuen them both vnto vs, to wit, bothe that he hath ſette the artes and ſciences againe in their perfection &amp; eſpecially ſince he hath reſtored the pure knowledge of hys heauenly doctrine to bring vs euen vnto him and to bryng vs in into his hie and merueilous ſecrets: if it come to paſſe that any in ſteade of takyng profyte thereof had rather wander ouer wharte the fieldes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepe themſelnes within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes are not they worthy to be double puniſhed? Which thing then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe in effect when they are ſo dull or rather ſo brutyſhe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they will applie their hole ſtudy to a foliſhe abuſe: wherein they do no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing but torment themſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any profit. I know wel inough their goodly titles wherewith they ſette vp and painte out ſo foliſhe a ſuperſtition. No man can denie but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcience of Aſtrologie is hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable. Therefore they couer them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues with this cloke. They name
<pb facs="tcp:7889:7"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Mathematiciens whych is as muche to ſay as profeſſers of the liberall ſciences. But none of thys is newe: for theyr forgoers haue alſo pretended the ſame to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intent they might deceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Yet when we haue perceiued &amp; as it were ſene with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eye that there is no ground in all their follie nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Aſtrologye nor yet of any ſcience we haue no occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why we ſhould be abaſhed at theſe maſques vnleſſe it were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would make litie children a fraide. But al thoſe whych haue any knowledge be it neuer ſo litle haue no great nede of this my aduertiſment to be iuſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to beware how they mell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Therefore this ſimple trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſhall rather be for the ſimple &amp; unlearned multitude whych might eaſelye be deceiued, becauſe they can not put a difference betwixte the right Aſtrologie and theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of charmers &amp; forcerers. Wherefore lette vs firſte ſee how ſarre the true Aſtrologie dothe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb facs="tcp:7889:7"/> it ſelf: which is the knowledg of the naturall order &amp; diſpoſition that God hath ſet in the ſtarres &amp; and planets to iudge of their office propertie and vertue &amp; to bring all to their end and vſe. We know wel enough what Moiſes faith: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God hath made the ſonne and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone to rule the daies and the nights: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moneths y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeares and all ſeaſons. In the which he doth comprehend all which toucheth either tilling of the erthe and. Huſbandry or ciuille policye. And as touching that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce &amp; trule whereof he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth it is moſt certaine that the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ignoraunt haue ſome taſte and feling but this ſcience of aſtrologie beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effectes dothe alſo declare the cauſes. As for example. The moſt rude &amp; ſimple people do playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perceiue that the daies are ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in winter then in ſumer: that it is whotte in ſumer and colde in winter: but they come neuer ſo his as to iudge how or wherefore that cometh to paſſe. All the world doth
<pb facs="tcp:7889:8"/> know the eclipſes of the ſonne and of the moone: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes are hide vnleſſe one haue learned them by doctrine and ſcience. We need not go to the ſcoole to ſee that ther are ſtarres in heauen. But it is not for al perſones to comprehend the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of their courſes their reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons theyr aſpectes and other lyke things: for that doth requir a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all knowledge. Wherefore the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trologie doth ſerue to diſcuſſe the courſe of the planetts and ſtarres, aſwell for the time as for their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuacion &amp; order. I ſaye that it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for the times becauſe we may knowe what ſpace of tyme euery planet yea and the firmament alſo dothe require to fulfil their courſe. Againe it ſerueth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſituacion, to knowe howe farre one is diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from an other to diſcerne the moci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons which are ſtreight or croked or one againſt an other: further more to knowe why the ſonne is rather further from vs in winter then in ſommer. and wherfore it tarieth
<pb facs="tcp:7889:8"/> longer ouer vs in ſommer then in winter. To know how to compaſſe and meaſure in what ſigne of the Zodiaque it is eueri moueth what aſpectes it and the other planets haue: wherfore the moone is in the full or in the weane according as ſhee either draweth from the ſonne or draweth nere: how eclipſes come yea it ſerueth thus farre euen to meaſure the degres &amp; the minutes. This ground being laid the effects which we ſe here beneth do folowe the which by the meanes of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie we knowe to come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue and that not onely when they are come but alſo we are aduertiſed be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they come. There is none but he heareth the noiſe of the windes and ſeeth the raine haile &amp; ſnowe: but none knoweth the cauſes ſaue onely by the meanes of Aſtrologie: which as I haue ſaide geueth alſo ſome coniectures for the tyme to como. Although that we may not make therof a general rule I ſpeak therfore of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinary courſe which
<pb facs="tcp:7889:9"/> is not letted by other accedents or chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces comming from ſome other cauſe. But well this is the matter which we haue to intreate of: for our feined Aſtrologians do take a principle which is true: to witte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the earthly bodies and generally all creatures which are vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen are ſubiecte to the order of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to draw from it ſome qualities Howbeit they applye it ful il. And thoghe the caſe were euen ſo, the naturall Aſtrologie wil ſhew well enough that the bodies which are here beneth doe receiue ſome infl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence of the moone, by that that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyſters are either full or empty as the moone is eyther in the full or weane. Likwiſe that the bones are either full of marowe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone is either in the ful or els weaneth. Likewiſe the phiſicians doe drawe out of the true Aſtrologye all the iudgement y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue to ordeyne bloode lettings or drinks or pilles &amp; other things in due time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt needes confeſſe that
<pb facs="tcp:7889:9"/> is a certain conuenience betwyxte the ſtarres or planets and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of mans body. And all this as I haue ſaid is conteined vnder the naturall Aſtrologie. But the ſhameles deceiuers which wold vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloke of the ſcience haue gone furder haue counterfeicted an other kynd whych they call Iudicialle, which conſiſteth in two princypall articles: whereof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt is to know not onely the nature and complexi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo al their fortunes as they call them, yea and all that they ſhal either do or ſuffer in ther life. The ſecond is what end thoſe matters ſhall haue which they go aboute when they traffike and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie one with an other and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of the whole eſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world But let vs firſt entreate of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexion of euery one according to his birthe. And as ther was neuer lie ſo great nor ſo impudent which will not borrowe ſome coulour of truthe: I graunt ſurely that as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the complexions of men and
<pb facs="tcp:7889:10"/> chiefly as concerning the affections which are partakers of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their bodies: that they part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly depend of the ſtarres or at leaſt haue ſome agreement therewith. As to ſay that a man is of a more coloricke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flegmaticke complexi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on or contrariwiſe. Neuertheleſſe euen in this ther are many things to be noted: Our Mathematiciens to whom I ſpeake doe found theyr iudgement vpon the houre in the which one is borne. But I ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe that the hour of the gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration is more to be conſidered the which for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part is vnknowen for the mother hath not allwais a time certaine wherein ſhe ſhoulde bring for the her childe. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they haue to reply agaynſt it yet for all that ſhall they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced by reaſon that the ſtarres haue not ſo greate force to prynt qualities in a man at his birthe as at his conception yea &amp; I ſay more ouer that putte the caſe the ſtarres did giue vs our qualities or proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:7889:10"/> by their influence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that doeth not come by our birthe for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune experience doeth proue it. Neither is it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out cauſe that Perſius ſaith <hi>Geminos Horoſcope Varo Producis genio.</hi> which is as muche to ſaie as that vnder the ſame Horoſcope or aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent two may be borne of diuerſe natures. Whych is allways ſene yea and that in brethren which are twynnes whych wyll ſo dyffer one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other as thogh the poſitions of the ſtarres had bene clene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary I will not ſay that to iudge ſurely by the natiuitie, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of a man beſide this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he muſt haue all the degrees of the Climate wel marked: moreouer this genethliak and teller of mens fortune by the ſtarres muſt haue his Aſtrolobe in his hand. For to truſt to the clocke or diall is ſcant ſure enough. For if one doe miſſe but a fewe minuts a man ſhall finde great chaunges in the beholding of the ſtarres. But whether it be that one muſt iudge by the conceiuing or by the birth it
<pb facs="tcp:7889:11"/> is no matter this I will aſke if the ſexe of male and famale do not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount all the reſt of the qualities which ar in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creature. But if this be true that in one moment and in one belly a ſonne &amp; a daughter ſhal be conceiued: yea &amp; in one moment one woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be brought to bedde of a man childe and an other of a woman childe. Whence cometh this diuerſitie which is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall? but that the ſtarres &amp; planets haue no ſuche power as thoſe felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes wolde haue men to beleue. If a man ſhoulde make a compariſon Ther is nothing more certaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſede of the father &amp; of the mother haue an influence and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an hundreth folde more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer then hath all the ſtarres toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, yet notwithſtanding a man may ſee that it faileth oftentimes, and the diſpoſytion alſo may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe. Let vs take two men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and diuerſe natures, hauing either of them a wyfe lykewiſe of a contrary complexion and nature, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7889:11"/> do begett children in the ſelfe ſame houre and are broght to bed in the ſelf ſame houre: it cometh common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to paſſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children wil take their complexion rather of their fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers &amp; mothers then of the aſpecte of the ſtarres which they both had like. And the reaſon is ſo euident that none of good iudgement wyll ſpeake any thing to the contrary. What ſhould we ſay then of the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluence that the ſtarres of heauen giue to men? I graunt (according to that that I touched before) that the ſtarres haue in deed ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to forme the complexions: &amp; ſpecially thoſe that concerne the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy: but for all that I denie that the principall cauſe cometh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſe. I vnderſtand as concerning natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes euen thoſe whiche they call inferior cauſes. For the ſeede, whereof the children are procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and made dothe goe before and is of greater importaunce. Second<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly I ſay that the Aſtrologians doe make an euill foundation, and are
<pb facs="tcp:7889:12"/> not of a ſure ground when thei wil rather iudge by the natyuitye and byrthe then by the generatyon and conceptyon, but it is true that the generatyon and conceptyon is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen vnto them, therfore haue they no certaynty of iudgement. Thirdly I ſay that God worketh in many by a ſpeciall grace euen in forming their nature, ſo that the conſtellation hath no place at all, or at the leaſt is ſo there exting wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and put out, that it can not be perceiued of men. Thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the natural inclination.</p>
            <p>But if we come to the grace that God geueth to his children, at ſuch tyme as he reformeth them by his holy ſpirite, and changeth them in ſuche ſorte that they are worthely named New Creatures: whereto ſerueth all the aſpecte and reſpects of the planets? Is this it wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God hath founded his eternall election? if the Byrthtellers &amp; caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars of mens natiuities wil alledge this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may vſe theſe things
<pb facs="tcp:7889:12"/> as inferior means. This is a very foliſhe cauillation. We do ſe how it hath pleaſed God of ſet purpoſe, to drawe vs backe from ſuche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, when he hath cauſed them to be borne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond place, whom he wolde preferre to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as we haue in the example of Iacob. For wherfore was it that Eſau which ſhuld be reiected came before: but that God in breaking the commune order of nature woulde lyfte our eyes more hyghe? Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing vs hereby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſte loke vp and faſten oure eyes vpon hys wyll only without tourning away to ſearhe other cauſes. Let vs only reſt vpon this, that God reformeth men in ſuche ſort, when he calleth them vnto hym that they become all together new It was ſpoken of ſaul when God wolde prepare him to be king that he wold make hym far otherways then he was. Thys came by no conſtellation, but God wroght in hym far aboue &amp; beyond the courſe of nature. And yf thys
<pb facs="tcp:7889:13"/> come to paſſe in a man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had choſen for the temporall regiment: what ſhall come to paſſe as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them whom he hath choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his children and heriters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kyngdome? Surely it muſt needes be that this doth ſurmount all the firmament and the ſtarres. And this is moſt certain that who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer dothe denye that regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a worke of God aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dothe not onely ſhewe that he is a profaine man: but alſo doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly renounce the faythe of the Chriſtians. Therefore we muſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite the forſe of the ſtarres by that which concerneth the worlde and doth apperteine to the body and is one of the firſt inclinations of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: excepting neuertheles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all gyftes that God gyueth to one aſwell as to an other without the ordinarye meanes: and ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformation that he maketh in his elect reneuing them by his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But this baſtardly aſtrology not contented to haue diſpoſed and ſet
<pb facs="tcp:7889:13"/> in order y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> complexion and maners of men: doth extend her iudgement further. Which is in foretelling y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which ſhall fal vpon them all their life longe, and the time and maner of their deathe. Wherein there is nothing but a raſhe boldnes and no reaſon at all. For at the moſte the ſtarres may emprinte certain qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in the perſones but they can not cauſe that this thing or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld fall vpon them aftrwarde of other occaſions. So now thogh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a birth reader cold iudge a man to be pain full and dilygent to gather ryches: yet can he not forſee that ſome heri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage ſhall fall vnto hym by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, becauſe that lyeth in the wil or condition of others and not of him ſelf. Behold then wherfore it was ſayd of olde, that theſe mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian maſkes are good to fil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares and to empty the purſſes: Becauſe that when they tel of good fortune they fede the curious wyth wynde and vanitie and drawe forth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſo euer they wyll after that
<pb facs="tcp:7889:14"/> once they haue bewitched them.</p>
            <p>Well they can tell a man how ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny wiues he ſhall haue: yea, but fynde they in their ſtarres the nati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie of his firſt wife, to know how long ſhe ſhall liue? By this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the women ſhoulde no more haue their peculiar natiuitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei ſhould be ſubiect to their huſbandes natiuitie. To be ſhorte by this meanes the Horoſcope or aſcendent in the byrth of one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſon ſhoulde comprehend the iudgement of the whole diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a contrey: ſeing that they boaſt themſelues that thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge if a man ſhall haue an happye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and whether he ſhall haue good or euil chaunce by the wayes and fieldes: into what dangers he ſhall fall: whether he ſhalbe ſlayne or dye in his bedde. Let vs regarde nowe with howe manye men we haue to doe wyth all in oure lyfe tyme. If the Sothſayers had not all their wylles, and their fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in their ſleues at commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:7889:14"/> what colde thei promiſe vs hereby? Therefore doe I conclude that all thoſe that take vpon them to knowe the fortune of one man by his natiuitie ar deceyuers of the people, in ſo much as the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes are not in him whoſe byrthes he caſteth, but in others. It ſhould be to longe to brynge all the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples that mighte be broughte, but one only may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>There dyeth many times in one battell thre ſcore thouſande men, I do not ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt great diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comfitures, but of ſuch as are very common, nowe I demande if that we muſte aſſigne to all theſe that are coupled together in their death the ſelfe ſame aſcendent in theyr byrth? When they wyll ſaye that one thing that commeth rare may not be preiudiciall to the common doctrine of an arte. This is but a ſhyfte eaſely to be auoyded. For I ſpeake vnto them of a common thing: the hiſtories do teſtifie that in twenty battels in Spaine there
<pb facs="tcp:7889:15"/> dyed about thre hundred thouſand men. And wythoute further way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng in the matter, who can not eaſly iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe that dyed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were far diuerſe in natiuitie in the eſpects &amp; reſpects of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars. So that in ſo greate a multitude Capricornus and the Ram and the Bulle dyd ſo iumble their hornes together that all was there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. Aquarius did powre out his water in ſuch aboundance that it was like a floode. The virgine had loſte her virginitie. The Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis went backewarde. The Lion ſtroke behinde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his taile in ſuche ſort that one could not perceyue it. The twinnes called Gemini, did ſo mingle them ſelues together as though they had bene one. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher did ſhute traiterouſlye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one were aware of hym. The Scales or Ballance was falſe.</p>
            <p>The fiſhes did hide them ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the water ſo that thei coulde be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſene no more. Neyther had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſting of Scorpio any force, vnles it were
<pb facs="tcp:7889:15"/> the cauſe of all thys murther. Yea whiche is a great deale worſe, thei are not content to haue ſpred their winges ſo farre abrode in mans na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuitie: but they do vſurpe the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, or rather the ſothſaying, and for tellyng of all enterpriſes. by the preſent aſpect of the ſtarres. As for example, if a man haue a iorney of two hundreth miles of, where he doth dwel, maiſter Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loger wyl gaze and ſpye by the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, to know when it will be good that this pore foole ſhuld depart to finde at .xv. dayes ende his familie ſafe &amp; wel diſpoſed when as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars which did promes him good ſucces ſhalbe out of their reigne &amp; domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I pray you if the ſtars had any powre to conducte and gyde mans enterpriſes ſhoulde we not rather haue regarde to them which then beare rule when the matter is a doyng? What foly is it to ſaye, yf I ought to bye marchandies of a man which is beyonde the ſea, that the ſtarre which ruleth at my
<pb facs="tcp:7889:16"/> departure ſhall giue me good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and they which rule when the bargaine is made can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng. I remembre the tale that they are wont to tell of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Farneſus who by the counſel of an aſtrologer was compelled to leaue his dinner to get on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe: to the entent that he might haue good ſucces in his embaſſage. And if he had departed two houres after hauing dined at his leaſure and had come that night to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame lodgyng: what woulde that either haue furthered or hyndered hym? who is it that doth not perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chiefeſt point is to know the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld end the matter? I meane yf there were anye controuerſitie whether we ought to beleue them or no. But we may eaſely perceyue that all is but a mere abuſe. I haue heard tell of certayne phantaſticall felowes which are in honor which durſt not get vpon their mules without thei had afore aſked leaue of the ſtars. Put the caſe it were a counſeller
<pb facs="tcp:7889:16"/> of ſome hie court: there is a certain time appoynted to aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there are twentye which are ſubiect to one rule &amp; law, &amp; yet for all that theyr ſtars are diuers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all together, what ſhall they doe? If men were ruled by Aſtrology they would be ſo far from euer endyng any proces and action that one ſhould not be able to bryng three Iudges together to here a mans cauſe. Therefore it muſt nedes be that either the ſtars muſt be remoued to the intent thei may otherwiſe agree or els that al policie ſhould be beaten downe.</p>
            <p>But we knowe that god doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue this order that there ſhoulde be certayne houres appoynted to kepe iuſtice to heare his worde to receyue the ſacramentes, without hauing regarde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oppoſition of heauen. If that in muſing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtarres men doe forſake the order which God hath appoynted, and that euery one go aſyde without accommodating hym ſelfe to the common ſocietie of mankind: ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:7889:17"/> not God be contrary to himſelfe? Where ſhall that incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wiſdome appeare by the which he hath ſo well ordered all thyngs that it doeth ſeeme that he hathe made all by line and meaſure? If one can not obey hym in thys one poynt, except he do contrary to the order which he hath placed in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? A man may very well applie that mery taunte to this kinde of men which an auncient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher heard of his maide, who whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he marked ouer earneſtly the ſtarres and the firmament, had no leaſure to loke to his fete, and ſo ſtumbled &amp; fel into a ditche. Then ſayde his mayde vnto hym, there is nothyng better then to thinke vpon thoſe thinges that are moſt neare vnto vs. I woulde not turne nor applye this taunt or mocke to the trewe Aſtrologians whoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and paine which thei haue taken to make vs know the ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of heauen, can neuer be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much praiſed: for ſomuch as it was
<pb facs="tcp:7889:17"/> good bothe to glorifie God and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſerue vs to our vſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. But for theſe ſpeculatiue fooles which walke aboue the clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, and in the meane ſeaſon doe not conſider whither God doth cal them, nor haue regarde of their du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, which (I ſaye) wander out of the way which God ſheweth them and forget their dutie which they owe to their neighbours: is there not good cauſe why one ſhoulde mock and deride their vanitie, and that God alſo ſhoulde make them ignominius and ſhameful &amp; cauſe them not onely to ſtumble, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the ende to fall and to breake their necks?</p>
            <p>After that theſe our good mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters the Genethliaks which tell mens fortunes by their birth, haue broght euery one of vs vnder their perticular iuriſdiction by Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my they vſurpe alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame power ouer the vniuerſall eſtate of the worlde. And ſurely I do confeſſe, accordynge to that that I haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:7889:18"/> ſayde that in ſo muche as the earthly bodies haue a certain agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: we mai well note that certaine cauſes in the ſtarres why thyngs come ſo to pas here beneth. For euen as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of heauen doth often times cauſe tempeſt whirle windes and chaunge of weather, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all raines: ſo conſequently it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth barrennes and peſtilences.</p>
            <p>Therefore in that that we ſee an order and as it were a knotte and tying together of the things whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ar aboue with the things that are beneth: I am not againſt but that one may ſeeke in the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creatures the begynnyng and cauſe of the accedentes which are ſene here in the earth. I take this worde beginninge not as the firſt and principall cauſe, but as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour meanes to Goddes wyll: yea, and ſuch a one as he vſeth as a preparation to accomplyſhe hys worke euen ſo as he determined in his eternall counſell. How be it we
<pb facs="tcp:7889:18"/> muſt not altogether deny but that there is ſometime a certaine agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a peſtilence which we ſee here and the influence of the ſtars which is knowen by Aſtrologye. Yet this in no caſe can be general: for when the choyſe was lefte to Dauid which of the thre roddes of God he woulde chuſe and that he had choſen the peſtilence: we may not ſay that that did procede of the ſtarres. Likewiſe when the famin was ſo great in Siria and in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell in the time of Elias and that the drought was there ſo longe: it were a point of great foliſhenes to ſeke wither the ſtarres were there vnto diſpoſed or no, ſynce it was an extraordinary miracle.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we take this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as one amonge others very rare: ſince God ſpeakyng general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the bokes of Moyſes: ſayeth that all aduerſities that come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n are hidde in his treaſures: Whereby he doeth ſignifie that he powreth them furthe, to puniſhe
<pb facs="tcp:7889:19"/> mans ſinnes: and that if ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his malice did not prouoke his wrath, he woulde ſhut them vp as it were in a coffer. And ſurely there is not anye more common doctrine tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all the Prophetes then this: to wit, that he wyl make the heauen and the earth as braſſe.</p>
            <p>And ſeyng he aſſigneth the cauſe to our ſinnes, all influence of the ſtarres is excluded. As for the war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, there is leſſe matter: why thei ſhould ſearche the cauſe in the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res wherfore they come, ſince they alſo are Gods ſcourges to correct ſynnes, which depende nothing of the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>God promiſing to Abraham that he woulde geue the lande of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan to his poſteritie, ſayth that the terme is not yet come. He doth not ſay that the aſpect of the ſtars doeth not beare it. What doeth he ſay then? He ſayth that the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ammorities is not yet com to the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore as men vſe to gather the fruicte of a tree
<pb facs="tcp:7889:19"/> when it is rype: euen ſo our ſinnes do haſten Goddes plagues. Nowe let vs ſee whether mans wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and tranſgreſſions do procede from the ſtarres. There haue bene of olde tyme certayne phantaſtical felowes, which did imagine it: but this madnes was iuſtly caſt aſyde by the whole worlde yea, and was counted a deuiliſhe inuencion the which all Chriſtians ought to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hore: as in dede it can not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued but all the holy Scripture muſt be ouerthrowen and god blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemed and libertye giuen vnto men to doe wickedly. Therefore I take this article as concluded that the contempt of god and the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions which are committed in any countrey that is in the earth haue reſpect to the ſtars. Which if it be ſo, we muſt alſo not attribute to the ſtarres Gods vengeaunce that commeth for ſuch cauſes.</p>
            <p>If they obiect that god can vſe the naturall meanes to chaſten men withall: I doe not denye it. But
<pb facs="tcp:7889:20"/> muſt we ſaye that this is done by a continuall order euen as the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res are therevnto prepared? No but contrarywiſe when God doth drye vp the redde ſea and the riuer Iordan although he did vouchſafe to vſe the winde proper to do it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all: yet it was not ſayde that that winde was ſtirred by any aſpect of the ſtarres: but that God did raiſe it vp at that preſent. Although I wyll wyllyngly agree with them in thys poynte that when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him he doth applie the nature and propertie of the ſtarres to his ſeruice. Onely I ſaye this that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther famines, peſtilences, nor war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, come at any tyme by the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition of the ſtarres: if it be not be cauſe god would declare his wrath vpon mankinde. And contrariwiſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboundance of good helth &amp; peace do not procede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> influe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtarres, but from the bleſſing of God, whether it be to exhorte &amp; brynge vs to repentaunce by ſuche gentilnes, or that he will cauſe vs
<pb facs="tcp:7889:20"/> to feele his loue when we obey his iuſtice. But let vs conclude vntyll theſe our counterfaite Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue ſhewed that the ſtarres either make vs to ſerue God or do ſtyrre vs vp to be rebelles and to reſiſt him: that they are neither cauſes of the good nor of the euyll whiche come vnto vs. For euerye one may ſee that the one foloweth of the other.</p>
            <p>Yf I would gather al the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which do agre with this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the booke ſhoulde haue none ende. And yet for all that there is none which may not eaſely of him ſelfe marke them and finde them out. Wherefore let vs learne to ſtaye oure ſelues on the promiſes and threateninges of God: which ſeing they nothing depende of the ſitutiation of the ſtarres do teache vs that we muſt not ſet our minde vpon the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>This is the cauſe that God by hys Prophet Eſay did mocke the Egiptians and Caldeans, whych
<pb facs="tcp:7889:21"/> for al that were the cunneſt nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this arte that euer were in the worlde: rebukyng them and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their charge that by al their ſcience they coulde not foreſee the deſolation which was nere to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it came not from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall courſe of the ſtarres, but of Gods ſecret iudgement. Neither can one obiect that he doth rebuke the men whiche dyd falſely boaſt they were conning in Aſtrologie. For he turneth himſelf namely to the arte, declaryng that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but vanitie.</p>
            <p>For when he ſpeaketh to the kyngdome of Egipte, he ſayeth:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 19. 12.</note> * where are nowe thy wyſe men? that they maye tell thee or maye know what the lord of hoſtes hath determined againſt Egipt.</p>
            <p>And yet there was no part of aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logie but it was there. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doeth as it were ſpeake in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite agaynſt all them that medle wyth it, ſayinge that it is not their office to knowe the thynges
<pb facs="tcp:7889:21"/> which come to paſſe as thei make profeſſion. There are more expres wordes when he ſpeaketh to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon.
*<note place="margin">Iſa 47. 13.</note> Thou arte weryed in the multitude of thy counſels: let now the Aſtrologers, the Stargaſers, and pronoſticatours, ſtand vp and ſaue thee from theſe thinges that ſhal come vpon thee. Beholde thei ſhall be as ſtubble: the fyre ſhall burne them.</p>
            <p>The Chaldeans were moſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed in Aſtrologie that euer were anye: ſo that all they which haue thruſte them ſelues into this curioſitie, did borowe their name from them. Wherfore we ſe howe God reproueth and condemneth them: and pronounceth playnlye that men can not learne of the ſtarres the mutations and falles of kyngdomes: and that he wyll puniſhe the pryde of them whiche haue thruſte themſelues in to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe it. Therefore he ſaith alſo by the ſame Prophet that he doth ſcatter abrod and bring to nought
<pb facs="tcp:7889:22"/> the ſignes of the Sothſayers: and make Enchaunters mad: that he wyll tourne the wiſe cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and make their ſcience fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes. He doeth not rebuke the raſhnes of them which ar not wel founded in the arte: but he doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe theyr principles and marimies: to wit this conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſtarres whereof he ſpeaketh in another place. Wherfore Dani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell entending to expounde Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadnezers dreame the whiche all the Aſtrologians and diuines cold not once attaine vnto: doeth not make him more wiſe then they in the arte nor yet more ſubtell. But he maketh their ſcience and the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelation of God, as it were, two contrary thinges. The Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſayth he, &amp; diuines could not declare the ſecret vnto thee: for it is God which is in heauen to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys doth appertaine, to wit to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare ſecretes. And to be ſhorte we ſee that this whole part of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy which doeth ſerue for diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:7889:22"/> called iudgement: is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counted of God as vaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profitable: but is alſo condemned as derogatynge from his honour and diminiſhing his glorye.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if we wil be of his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple let vs harken what he ſayth in his Prophet Ieremy: *<note place="margin">Iere. 10. 2.</note> let vs not be lyke the Heathen, fearyng the ſygnes of heauen. I knowe well inough the ſhifte that certaine do bring: to witte, that we muſt not feare the ſtarres as though they had rule ouer vs: and yet for all that they doe not ceaſe to haue a certayne perticular ſuperioritie vnder the hande and gouernaunce of God. But there is no dout but that the Prophet woulde bring vs to the prouidence of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the intent he might bring to paſſe, he goth about to bring vs from the vaine care that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men did torment themſelues withal: for aſmuch as he ſpeaketh to the Iſraelites which were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to geue themſelues to ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:7889:23"/> follye by the example of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans and Egiptians. Let a man aſke nowe a dayes a Genethliake from what ſprynge their arte is come. They can not deny but Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon was the fountaine: and that that which they know is but as it were litle ryuers which runne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence. Therefore ſince God hath once forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people to be like to theſe mens predeceſſoures and maſters: ſhall we doe well if we be lieue theſe their inferiers? Thogh there were none othere euell but this, that in attributyng the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our proſperous ſucceſſe and afflictions to the ſtarres and to their influence, we put as it were cloudes before oure eyes to driue vs awaye from the prouidence of God: we maye already ſee that it is a thyng ouer dangerous to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle withall. But more ouer thys foloweth that thoſe men whiche wander amongeſt the ſtarres, doe deſcende no more into their owne conſciences to examine their life:
<pb facs="tcp:7889:23"/> although they know that they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye within themſelues the matter and cauſe of all euyll, and theyr ſynnes are the woode to kyndle Gods wrathe, for the which wars famine, peſtilence, hayle, froſt and other lyke thynges do come.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they that loke for good lucke by the prediction of the ſtars reſtyng fully vpon them: do wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw theyr hope from God and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come ſluggiſhe to demaunde it, as though they had alreadye wonne that which they looked for. I am not ignoraunt what they haue to ſay againſt it and to cauill. They wyll alledge a ſaying of Ptolome, that the ſignifications of ſtarres are not lyke the decrees of a parla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment which ſhould haue their exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cution ready: becauſe god is aboue them. But when they haue ſayde all that they can this is but a ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hole: for ſeyng all the euylles wherewith the ſtarres threaten vs do procede from the order of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture: we muſt nedes conceyue this
<pb facs="tcp:7889:24"/> phantaſie that our ſinnes are not then the cauſe.</p>
            <p>I wyll let paſſe the abſurditie and contradiction that is in theyr wordes: to witte, that the order which God hath appoynted to be euerlaſtyng is changed by cauſes that come by chaunce. As though god were contrary to himſelfe. It is inough for me that I haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde of the Prophet which is that he doth ſet forth, as it wer two contrary thynges the reſpect which the Heathen haue to the ſtarres in imaginynge that theyr condition and eſtate of their lyfe dyd whollye depende thereon: and the knowledge on the which the faithfull oughte to reſt to witte, that they are in the hande of God and that he wyll bleſſe them yf they ſerue him with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all the euils that they ſuſteine are ſo many puniſhments for theyr ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Our Genethliaks thinke they haue a great ſolution in that the
<pb facs="tcp:7889:24"/> prophet nameth the ſtarres ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for thence they conclude that theyr office is to ſignifie thynges before they come.</p>
            <p>And for confirmation of that, they alledge that whiche is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the firſt chapter of Geneſis to wit, that God created them to this ende. But ſince they make ſo great bragges of this word ſignes what wyll they ſay to that which is written in Eſay *<note place="margin">Iſa. 44. 2</note> that God do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth deſtroye the ſignes of the diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners? It is moſte certaine that he ſpeaketh there of the Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. So if I confeſſe to them that they maye haue ſignes but that God wyll ouerthrowe them: what haue they gayned?</p>
            <p>Moreouer this cauillation is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer impudent to ſaye that Ieremy doeth after a ſorte confeſſe that there is ſome ſignification in the ſtarres, becauſe he calleth them ſignes. Yea, and it is a common kinde of ſpeche in rebuking an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, to vſe the wordes cuſtomable
<pb facs="tcp:7889:25"/> amongeſt them whome they wyll rebuke.</p>
            <p>The ſcripture calleth the Idols the heathen mens Goddes. Yf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnder pretenſe of that name, would proue the Idols to be gods who is it that woulde not mocke his foliſhenes? Brieflye: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete doeth admoniſhe the people that they ſhoulde not be troubled nor vexed with this opinion of the Heathen: that the ſtarres ſhould ſignifie this or that. As alſo at this preſente we can not rebuke this errour, but we muſt ſay that we muſte not occupie our mindes with ſuch ſignifications.</p>
            <p>As for the texte of Moyſes they pull it in peces whileſt they wyll ſtretche it to their folyſhe phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye: God hath ordeyned the ſtarres to be ſygnes. But we muſt marke of what thynges: how be it euerye one of ſounde iudgement doth wel inough vnderſtande that Moyſes would haue touched that which I haue heretofore declared, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:7889:25"/> the true vſe of Aſtrologye.</p>
            <p>Although the ſtarres be ſignes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs to ſhewe vs times to ſow or plant, to let bloode or to miniſter Phiſike and to cut wood, yet for al that thei are no ſignes to know when we ſhould put on new gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: whether we ſhoulde hys and ſell the Mondaye rather then the Tweſday and other like thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche haue no reſpect nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grement with the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>Therefore as we do confeſſe the naturall ſygnes: ſo as we deteſt the ſorcerie that the Deuyll hath inuented.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is an impudent ſlaunder wherewith they ſlaunder vs, in that they go about to make men beleue that we do deſtroy the order which God hath eſtabliſhed in takyng awaye from the ſtarres the propertie that they haue to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie things afore hand: yea that we condemne a very excellent and profitable ſcience. All this cloke is taken away in one word: when
<pb facs="tcp:7889:26"/> we put a difference betwixte the naturall Aſtrologie and this ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly Aſtrologye which the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians haue fayned. I know that to knowe the courſe of the ſtarres their vertue, and that which is of this ſort is not onely very profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to men: but alſo doth ſtyrre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to magnifie the name of God in his wonderfull wiſedom which he ſheweth there.</p>
            <p>For although the very ignorant and Idiots can not lifte vp theyr eyes to heauen but they ſhal haue great occaſion to glorifie God: yet thei which haue ſtudied to compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hend the ſecretes of nature, which are not knowen of all men, ought to be a great deale more ſtyrred vp to doe their dutye. But it is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter to ſpeake of the right and moderat vſe, and to ſpeake of the abuſe and exceſſe.</p>
            <p>If any man woulde in praiſing of Wine, allowe dronkenneſſe: woulde not all the worlde riſe by againſt him, becauſe he ſhoulde be
<pb facs="tcp:7889:26"/> a wicked corrupter of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes? The ſame do they which do borow or rather ſteale the tytle of a good and approued ſcience, to co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour certaine phantaſticall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations cleane contrarye to the truth of the ſcience which they do boaſt of. And ſurelye I preuented their ſubtiltie in the beginning, when I made a proteſtation that I woulde not onely reiect the art, which hath her beginning in the order of nature: but alſo that I do eſteme it and prayſe it as a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gifte of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore when the Genethli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aks would haue their gew gwaes and folyſhe toyes to be of forſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der pretence that it is a holye and good thyng to conſider the works of god: let euery one be warned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſhould bring them to this point and not ſuffer himſelfe to be cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the waye by their far fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched circumſtances. But they doe euen as the Alchumiſtes which do inſinuate them ſelues by long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces
<pb facs="tcp:7889:27"/> of the temperature of the ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes and of the agrement whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is amongeſt them and other lyke thinges which are trew and founded on good reaſon.</p>
            <p>But after they haue long gone about the buſhe, at length thei do nothyng but bable and giue vaine wordes: and then they haue done.</p>
            <p>And to be ſhorte ſince that the heauens ſhuld ſhew forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of God, &amp; the firmament ought to be as it were a glaſſe, to beholde his vertue and infinite wiſedome therin: let vs learn if we wil make our profite well of this, not to go wanderyng about in our imagina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions whyche ſhoulde bryng vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from God.</p>
            <p>But our Mathematicians do ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect that Ioſeph, Moyſes and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell, were taught in the ſcoles of the Egiptians and Caldeans: and that thei did rehearſe this of them ſelues to their praiſes and not as a vicious and noughtye thing. As for Ioſeph I anſwere that he doth
<pb facs="tcp:7889:27"/> faine himſelfe to be a diuine, but he did that vnder a colour, as alſo euery one may ſee that for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time he doeth diſguiſe himſelfe before his brethren.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, when that he foretelleth the famine of Egipte, dyd he coniecture that by the ſtars No but contrariwiſe he knew that by a wonderfull reuelation. For lo the Egiptians which had ſoght euen the vtmoſte parte of heauen to knowe howe they ſhoulde fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell thoſe thinges which were ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified by the ſtarres: yet for all that knew nothyng of this famin and might haue bene taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with afore they coulde haue once thought on it. God doth admoniſh Pharao by a dreame. Ioſeph doth declare vnto him that which was reueled vnto him by God. Is ther any thyng I praye you in all thys whiche doeth fauoure them that make it their Buckeler? As for Moyſes it is ſayd that he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in all the wiſedome of the
<pb facs="tcp:7889:28"/> Egiptians: but muſt that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode of their ſuperſtitions?</p>
            <p>Nowe I place this curioſitie to foretell thynges by the ſtarres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the worſte ſuperſtitions that they had. But to the intent this dout maye be taken awaye, let vs ſee whether Moyſes dyd helpe him ſelfe wyth thys ſcience in all his enterpriſes. When he ſhoulde brynge the people out of captiuitie dyd he take the ſtarres for his guydes? Likewiſe when he paſſed ouer the redde ſea? Final<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in al that God did by his hande was he euer guyded by this ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? He was alwayes ruled by the mouth of God hauyng alwais reſpect to the promiſe of the tyme of deliueraunce: and attemptyng nothing but that which was agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to that whiche was reueled him. Daniell alſo was ſkylfull in the art of the Chaldeans: but we doe not ſee that he dyd deſire to knowe more then the naturall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie. And ſure to make ſhorte
<pb facs="tcp:7889:28"/> there is no doute but that GOD when he ſpeaketh ſo often of theſe foretellers of thinges would haue expreſſelye condemned the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion as well of Egypte as of Chaldee by the which the people of Iſraell mighte haue bene cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
            <p>Therefore when the Genethli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aks to the intent they may honor their ſcience do put forth this aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cientie: this is all that they get by it, to wit, that euerye bodye kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth it is a curioſiotie which God reproueth. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he hath ſtreit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly forbidden his church to vſe. And moreouer they do great iniurie to the holye Patriarches whom they wyll wyth falſe lyes brynge into their company.</p>
            <p>They helpe them ſelues alſo with the ſentence of our Sauiour Chriſt ſayinge: that there ſhall be ſignes in heauen to tell the day of his laſt comming. But thei ſpeake of this as Clarkes and Scolers do talke of warres: trueth it is that
<pb facs="tcp:7889:29"/> we ſhoulde pardon them ſince it is not their wonte to talke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture, but to prattell of other thynges. Yea in dede we ought to forgeue them if they did abſtaine from defylynge it in the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of it as they doe.</p>
            <p>Howe be it this ſcripture doeth ſo lytle fauour them that we may tourne it againſt them. For oure Sauiour Chriſt doeth not ſpeake there of any conſtellation proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng from the courſe of nature: but rather of an extraordinarye thyng which doeth nothyng agre with it. Yea, and the Prophetes when they wyll declare how fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the wrath of the Lorde ſhalbe do vſe ſuch kynde of ſpeaches: that the Sunne ſhall be darkened and the Moone ſhall geue her light no more. It is moſt certain y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was ſene ſo to come to paſſe ſo often as God did plague his churche. And yet in the latter day which oght to bryng the perfection of all thyngs there ſhalbe viſible ſignes, aſwell
<pb facs="tcp:7889:29"/> to admoniſhe the faithfull as to make the vnfaithfull more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſable. But how ſo euer the matter go thys poynt ought to be as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that the ſignes and tokens wherof he maketh mencion there can not be comprehended by the courſe of the Starres: ſince that God wyll ſende them as thinges properly and perticularlye belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to that time.</p>
            <p>Yea, and moreouer: that they wyll import chaunge of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon order vpon the which the Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethliaks doe pretende that they are founded.</p>
            <p>The ſame oughte to be ſayde of the Starre whiche did appeare to the Philoſophers which cam from the Eaſt. And it is a greate moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage to attribute that to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature that the ſcripture doeth rehearſe for the miracles.</p>
            <p>Shall they ſaye that accordyng to their ſcience there might a ſtarre aryſe which ſhoulde go towardes Iewry, and then right to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.
<pb facs="tcp:7889:30"/> Yea, and that it ſhoulde va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe away, and that a lytle while after it ſhoulde appeare agayne, that it ſhoulde goe to Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem, and that it ſhould ſtand vpon one certain houſe to marke it out? Yea and that which is more, that it ſhoulde kepe her compas there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after as the men whom it guyded were able to go? When they haue well ſought the heauens thei ſhal fynde nothyng there, but it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a fixed ſtarre or els a plannet. It muſt needes then be aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by conſequent aboue the nature of Aſtrologye. And nowe what is more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then to drawe a ſingular priuilege to a general law? Who is it that doth not ſee their impudencie ſo well that they mocke them when they do argue after this ſorte: God dyd by a miracle ſet a ſtarre to guyde the Philoſophers which came to worſhyp his ſonne, and gaue it a courſe agreable to their iourney, which neither was like to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral mocion of heauen nor to the
<pb facs="tcp:7889:30"/> mocion of the planettes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it foloweth, that the ſtarres doe declare the condition and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of euery one of vs, and that by their influence all oure life is gouerned. We nede not any great ſubteltie to rebuke ſuch a beaſtly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And if there were none other thing but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet one might ſee how ſtable the foundations are where vpon thei leane.</p>
            <p>But to the intent that euerye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one maye better vnderſtande the wickednes which here is hidde as venim in the ſerpentes taile: it is good to vnderſtand that they mak no daunger to make all Chriſtian religion as wel ſubiect to the ſtars as mens bodies. For they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to render a reaſon wherefore. Mahomet and hys Alcoran hath a greater dominion then Chriſte and his goſpel: to wit, becauſe the aſpect of the ſtarres is more fauou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable to the one then to the other. What an abhomination is that? The Goſpell is Gods Scepter by
<pb facs="tcp:7889:31"/> the which he raigneth ouer vs: it is the vertue of his arme, whiche he openeth, as Sainct Paul ſayth for the ſaluation to all beleuers: it is his ſtedfaſte trueth vnder the which all the angels of Paradiſe ought to be humbled: the holy goſt is he who maketh it to profite ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng it forſe and victorie againſt all that reſiſt it, againſt the Deuyl and the worlde.</p>
            <p>But theſe phantaſtical felowes ſay that ſome corner of ſome ſigne of the Zodiak doeth cauſe man to beleue it. Contrariwiſe the ſect of Mahomet as the Scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs is a iuſt plague of God to puniſh the ingratitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And yet they wyll make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that it is ſet vp and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the diſpoſition of the ſtars. To be ſhorte it is euident that all they which mainteyne ſuch mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes know not what it is to ſpeake of God and his religion, no more then brute beaſtes.</p>
            <p>But to the intent they myghte
<pb facs="tcp:7889:31"/> make all thynges ſerue them as men famiſhed vſe to doe, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the eclipſes and comettes: and ſaye that if they haue any ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation then we may ſaye the ſame of the reſt of the ſtarres. I anſwer that as for the eclipſes if they be naturall they haue no ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: vnleſſe it be that they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender raine or winde or a whirle winde, or ſuch like: accordyng as we haue afore expreſſed. But we will ſuffer fooles to imagine that one may by them foreſhewe what ſhall chaunce to kingdomes, digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties: yea and to perticular perſons</p>
            <p>Now we read that it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſometymes that ſome ſkilfull man in Aſtrologye ſhoulde warne the armye of the Romaines of the Eclipſe of the Moone which ſhuld be: to the entent that the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars which ignorant in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, might not be troubled as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome euyll ſigne or token.</p>
            <p>We ſee then that the true aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logye doth take awaye the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition
<pb facs="tcp:7889:32"/> that theſe mad men do go aboute to bringe in againe.*<note place="margin">As did C. Sulpitius Gallus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bun<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> As for the wonderfull Eclipſes, as that which came at the deathe of oure lord Ieſus: I do not deny but that they haue certayne ſignifications. But that dothe ſo lytle ſerue for oure deuiners that it is rather to ſtoppe and beate downe their ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng. For if it be neceſſarye that there ſhoulde be an extraordinary miracle to ſignifie thinges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande, howe wyll they fynde that propertie and force in the common order? It is almoſt the lyke in the comettes although it be not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo. For they are inflamaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous which are engendred natural<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye: not at any certaine tyme, but as it pleaſeth God. Wherein one may ſee how much the comets do differ from the ſtarres: ſince that they are engendred by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall cauſes. And yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I wil not agre with them in this that their foretellyng are certaine, as alſo verye experience
<pb facs="tcp:7889:32"/> doth ſhewe it. For if a comet do ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare and ſoone after ſome noble man die: the people wil ſay that it came to ſommon him to appeare. But if the death of no noble man do folowe, they wyll let it paſſe, and neuer ſpeake on it. And yet neuertheleſſe, I do not denye but that when God wyll ſtretche out his hande to execute ſome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment worthy to be remembred in the worlde, he wyll ſome tymes admoniſhe vs by comets: but that doth nothing ſerue to bynde men and theyr condicion to a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all influence of heauen.</p>
            <p>Now it remaineth that we ſhuld anſwere to the examples whych they alledge to vs. And ſurelye it woulde ſeme that theyr arte were wholly approued by them. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt all others, there is one that maketh all them aſtoniſhed that reade him: to wit, of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician called Aſcletarius, which foretold that Domician the Emperour ſhould be kylled. But
<pb facs="tcp:7889:33"/> Domician being angry with him, called him and ſayde vnto hym: that ſince he occupied himſelfe ſo muche in diuining of others, that he ſhoulde diuine alſo of himſelfe. He anſwered the hour of his death was at hande and that his bodye ſhoulde be pulled in peces of the dogges. Domician maketh him to be kylled: and doeth commaunde that he ſhoulde be burnt to the en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent they might bury his aſhes as they were wont.</p>
            <p>But lo ſuch a ſtorme came ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly that it did put out the fyre, &amp; dogges fell to eate the body. But within a while after, Domician was killed. Moreouer, that which thei ſay of Iulius Ceſar &amp; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thematician Spurina, is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo merueilous: although it come ſome thing neare. For he did admoniſhe Ceſar that he ſhoulde beware of the fyrſt day of Marche. But the daye beynge come, Ceſar ſaide vnto him: Loe the firſt day of Marche is com. The other anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:7889:33"/> it is not yet paſſed. And ſurely Ceſar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenat was ther ſlaine. Thus our Genethliakes thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they haue won y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fielde ſo that none can reſiſt them to wit, that they can ſhewe that there is a ſure trueth in their arte. But I will aſke them if they thinke none other were borne in Rome and in Italy the ſame daye &amp; at the ſame houre wherein Iulius Ceſar was borne? And it is like that manye were borne vnder one ſelfe ſame Horoſcope. The ſame may be ſaid of Domician. But did they al ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore dye in the ſame day? Or had they a violent death? No but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe euen as the ſame horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope did not make them all Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſo likewiſe it did not cauſe that they ſhoulde all dye one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of death. Therfore we may ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is neither reaſon nor truth in their art: for if there wer any it wold take place euery where. But we ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſomtime .xxx. are borne at one time, one dyeth at twenty an
<pb facs="tcp:7889:34"/> other at fiftye: one of an ague, the other in the warre. Likewiſe afore they die, euery one hath his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kind of life, and his ſtate doth differ from euerye mans eſtate.</p>
            <p>And what hath euery one his own ſtarre in heauen, wherein he may learne what ſhall come vnto him? For if the conſtellacion coulde doe any thynge it woulde be equall in euery one. After the ſame ſort that may eaſily be refuted whiche they allege of Auguſtus the Emperore who hauing heard Theogines ſai that his natiuitie did promes him the Empyre of Rome. And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of this he coyned his money with the ſigne of Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne vnder the whiche he was borne. Who will doute but that many poore wretches were borne vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſigne, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome was a ſwineheard, another a nete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hard, &amp; euery one in ſuch a kind of empyre &amp; dominion? Yf the horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope or the reſpect of the ſtarres had gyuen the Romaine Empire
<pb facs="tcp:7889:34"/> to all them which were borne the ſame time that Auguſtus was: there woulde haue ben but a lytle portion left him. Whereof I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuinations which haue ben, wer founded nether vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon nor vpon ſcience. Thei wil obiect that yet for all that we ſee the trueth by the iſſue. I anſwere that that doeth nothyng ſerue to proue their art lawfull. But we do onely ſtande vpon this poynct, that it is a wicked curioſitie and reproued of God: and not whether that diuines did ſome times ſaye true or no. Truth it is that al whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch commeth from the Diuill is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing but lies: but God doth often tymes ſuffer that theſe deceiuers do ſay the truth, when as he wyll by this meanes puniſhe the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie and vnbelefe of the wicked Let vs take for them bothe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Sorcereſſe whereof Samuell ſpeaketh. For that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch ſhe ſayde to Saul came ſure to paſſe. But ſhall we therefore ſaye
<pb facs="tcp:7889:35"/> that ſhe had a ſcience founded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſon whereby ſhe could fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell hidde thinges? No for God by his iuſte vengeaunce did louſe for that preſent the brydle to Satan to the intente that that wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked king ſhoulde be deceyued euen as he was worthye. Likewiſe we oughte not to iudge that becauſe ſhe ſayd the trueth, that therefore it is lawful for the children of god to vſe ſuche meanes. For it is not after this ſorte that God woulde we ſhoulde knowe thoſe thynges which ar expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs to know.</p>
            <p>And of thys we haue a generall rule in the .xiii. of Deuteronomie: where it is ſayde that if any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doe foretell thinges which af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter come to paſſe: Yet if that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretenſe that he hath told the trueth, he woulde bring vs to the ſeruice of ſtraunge Gods, we ſhoulde not cleaue vnto him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth proue vs whether we loue him or no.</p>
            <p>Let vs well wey this worde, to
<pb facs="tcp:7889:35"/> wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what colour or appearance of the trueth ſo euer thoſe thinges haue which are contrary to God, and which he doth reproue by hys worde: yet that he which walketh in a good conſcience maye wel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of ſuch things and that ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be none deceiued by them but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the infidels and hypocrites: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that as Sainct Paule ſayeth<note place="margin">2. Teſſa. 3.</note> it is mete that they which wil not felowe the lyght ſhoulde walke in darkeneſſe. To be ſhorte, I do no more regarde all the true thinges which the Mathematicians haue afore tolde then the falſe miracles wherwith Pharaos Magicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s did reſiſt Moyſes, and by the which Chriſt hath foreſayd that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhould be deceyued.</p>
            <p>But as it is a horrible and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les laboryng to be wrapped in all the follies and ſuperſtitions in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which men do wrap them ſelues after that thei haue once let louſe the bridle to their curioſitie many light headed felowes hauing giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7889:36"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes wholy to diuine &amp; foretel things by the ſtars they do thruſt them ſelues yet further in to all kind of diuinations for after that thei are once entiſed withone ther is no deceite of the deuel ſo greate wherein they are not delited, but to the entent they myghte make their diueliſhe arte to ſeme good, thei couer it with the name of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon as though he had ben a ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerer And ſurely the ſcripture ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mencion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learning which he had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe ſecrets of nature, but it doth not ſay that he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuiner. And in very deed we ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the generall condemnation, that moyſes doth ſo oftene pronounce againſt al them which do occupye this art. Chiefly in the eightenth chapter of deuteronomie: where it is ſaid, loke there be no deuiner which doth deuine &amp; fortel things be found amongeſt you: nor obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of dais nor that haith reſpecte to birdes nor wich, nor coniurer, which doth coniure nor any which
<pb facs="tcp:7889:36"/> doth conſulte and aſke councell of familiar ſpirits nor coniuring the dead: for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do ſo are an abomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto god. And for theſe ſins he dyd deſtroye the nations which dwelt in this land, let vs allwais remembre that doctrine which I haue afore taught that God hath reſpecte to the Egiptians and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demneth them to the entent that he may bring his people from all their acuſtomed matters wherfore he doth condemne al the Iudiciall aſtrologie which paſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes of the true ſcience in deuining, &amp; fortelling things and likewiſe all witchecrafte, for ſomuche as that word doth emporte the reuelacion of hid thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which is don by wich crafte, or coniuringe of ſpirites, or by other like vanitie. And let vs note this that God did not con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent himſelfe with on word alone but ſeing that mans nature is ſo readye to runne hither &amp; thether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vanities to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entente he might better take away all refuges and
<pb facs="tcp:7889:37"/> ſtartinge holes he reckeneth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinds which were then knowen: yea, and he vſeth certaine names which at that tyme were honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as <hi>Roſem</hi> which <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s taken for hym that reueileth things, and ſomtymes is applyed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes which do forwarne things that are yet hyd &amp; ſecrete. Againe <hi>Chober,</hi> which ſignifieth to ioyne together, &amp; is ſpoken of him which can gather together &amp; place in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the coniunctions: whereby is ment without dout the Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that can driue the ſtarres into their places, whether thei be in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition or ſtande byas, to cauſe them to haue their aſpectes one to another. Alſo <hi>Idoni</hi> which ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifieth one of knowledge or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. As we ſee howe they take vpon them knowledge &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh abrode their folies, as thogh there were no other Science: or knowledge in al the world: yet do we ſe what god pronunceth therof and the horrible thretning where
<pb facs="tcp:7889:37"/> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth manace it, which ought to make them al to tremble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fear him. Now if euery kind of diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be thus reproued, what ſhall becom of them that dare medle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coniuring of ſpirites to enquire of things vnknowen? For a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſee that to be a ſorcery moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding ther are ſom ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meles, that thei do attribute their circle &amp; other enchantments vnto Salomon, and alſo they do allege that ſeing the ſpirits are ordeined to be miniſters vnto the faithfull, there can be no euyl in coniuryng them to ſerue vs thereby. But w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what faith is it that they do waite to be ſerued of them in ſuch forte, ſeing that it is againſt the expres commaundement of god. For it is ſo vnlawful vnto vs, to vſe any ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cret coniuratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angels to ſpeake vnto vs, that it is curſed ſuperſtitions to call vpon them in what maner ſo euer it be: of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part who hath ſolde or hired forth vnto them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil to be their
<pb facs="tcp:7889:38"/> verlets and ſeruants? for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of God counte them as theyr mortall enemies and oght to flye them and dryue them away from them, &amp; in no caſe to deſire or ſeke for anye acquantance with them muche leſſe to haue ani of them as a familier. Thoſe men then that wil haue them to be their ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhall fynde in the end that thei haue played and bourded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr maiſters. Therfore let vs conclud according to the word of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all diuinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſoth ſaying is wicked &amp; deteſtable ſacriledge: for he compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt his word<note place="margin">1. Samu. 15.</note> to ſothſaying and ydolatry to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne.<note place="margin">Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus.</note> it ſo much as is poſſible. Wherfore it is not without good reaſon that the ciuill lawes do ſo ſore condemne the Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.<note place="margin">Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſult a ſothſayer or mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c Suplitio ca petis feria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</note> And we mai not ſay that this is for the abuſe of the diſceyuers or yet that the name was odious to the ignorant: for god as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge of the policie of Iſraell: hath made a law more ſtrait againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that
<pb facs="tcp:7889:38"/> is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thei ſhalbe put to death &amp; al that hath to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. Leuit .xx. But let vs put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this wer a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g permitted by men: ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſo much deteſteth &amp; abhorreth it, what foly is it ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to go about to ioyne it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anitie as if a man wold ioyne fyre and water together. And this is a meruelous matter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus which had ben geuen to foliſh curioſities aſſone as thei had recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the faith, brent their bokes as S. Luke reciteth in the actes: and that ther ſhuld now be men ſo per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of Ieſus Chriſt ſhuld ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but to quicken their ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petites to ſerch al light &amp; vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vanities: this is a mer<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>us great diuerſity that the one ſort ſo ſone as thei had the goſpel, caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way al the diuinations &amp; ſothſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings wherin thei had ben brought vp al their life, &amp; that theſe others vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadow &amp; colour that they know the truth of God ſhould be ſtirred vp to giue them ſelf vnto it
<pb facs="tcp:7889:39"/> that neuer knew what it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And that thoſe vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Luke ſpeaketh did burne their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to the value of fiue. M. franks and that theſe men are ſo enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a vain imagination whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch they haue now conceyued that herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei wil conſume al their ſubſtance. Yet here is to be noted that S. Luke ſaieth not that they wer wicked or diuiliſhe artes, but he nameth them <hi>Periarga</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth light and vnprofitable curi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oſities. Although in very dede thei are wicked, yet doeth he ſpeake thus to the end to ſtop their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes that ſeke nothing els but ſtar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting holes as we know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians do: the which are ſo much worſe then their father Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon the Magician, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of Ieſus Chriſt was ſo aſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nied that he did nothing regarde his owne art. And though he were ſo wicked that he would w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> money bye the grace of gods holy ſpirite: yet for al that he did acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:7889:39"/> that the vertue of the ſonne of god did darken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcience y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he thought he had. But theſe hauynge bene lyghtened by God to knowe hys truth, do turne away their eyes &amp; do caſt them into deadly darkenes and had rather be in the darkenes of theyr lies, then to enioy the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly light in the which we haue ſaluation and lyfe euerlaſtyng.</p>
            <p>But what remedye is there for ſuch euils? ſurely this that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, which S. Paul doth recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend to vs ſhould be in ſtede of a bridle to kepe vs in the pure obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of god. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entent we maye doe that let euery one kepe that ineſtimable treaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in a good conſcience. For it is moſt certaine that the fear of God ſhalbe a good defence to defend vs from all errours. So that we haue firſt this generall rule to ſanctifie our bodies &amp; our ſoules to god &amp; to ſerue him vnfainedly. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that euery one loke wherto he is called to the end he maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb facs="tcp:7889:40"/> himſelf to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which it becometh him to do. That learned men doe geue them ſelues to good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſtudies and not to foliſh cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rioſities which ſerue for none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ende then to make fooles to muſe at them. That lytle &amp; great, learned, &amp; vnlearned may thinke that we are not borne to the ende, that we ſhould occupye our ſelues about vnprofitable thinges: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ende of our exerciſes ought to edifie bothe our ſelues and others in the fear of god. And ſurely whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſhall well marke the matter: who are they that bring vs this er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ronious and falſe Aſtrologye ſaue only either proude parſons, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, that are neuer content or idle perſones which knowe not of what they ſhuld talke, or in what they ſhould haue their paſtime?</p>
            <p>Such as are the clarkes &amp; ſecreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ladyes &amp; other fine &amp; denty minio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the court. Not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei are cunning in this art (if ther may be any cunning in madnes &amp; lies) but
<pb facs="tcp:7889:40"/> it is inough for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lightly to haue touched it, and to haue bene buſye about it: and in the meane ſeaſon they entangle &amp; wrap many pore ſoules in theyr deceytes.</p>
            <p>And this is the cauſe wherefore I ſaide that we muſt occupye our ſelues in more profitable things: for who ſoeuer ſhal giue him ſelfe to fear God &amp; wil ſtudy to knowe what is his will, exerciſing him ſelfe in the practiſe of that which the holy ſcripture doth teache vs &amp; ſecondly ſhall apply his whoole mind to that which apperteineth to his vocation or at the leaſte to good and profitable things: ſhall haue no leaſer to fly into the ayre to the entent he might goe hether and thether in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes and yet for all that neither touche heauen nor earthe. I knowe well enough that they will not faile to vſe this cauillation for they will ſay that the one doth not hinder the other. To the which I aunſwer that no good ſcience is contrarye to the
<pb facs="tcp:7889:41"/> feare of god, nor yet to the doctrine which he giueth vs to bring vs in to euerlaſtinge life, ſo that we do not put the carte before the horſe: that is to ſay: that we haue this wiſdom that we vſe theſe artes to ſerue vs whether they be liberall or handycrafte, whiles we paſſe through this worlde to haſt conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. But here we haue ſpoken &amp; treated of a curioſitie not onelye ſuperfluous and vnprofitable: but alſo euill &amp; wicked: ſeinge it dothe driue vs away both from the truſt and confidence that we ought to haue in God and from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration that he would y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould haue both of his iuſtice mercy and iudgment and alſo of the duty which we do owe to our neighbours.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7889:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
